Guide to the Arnold Genthe Photograph Collection [1895]-1942 (Bulk 1906-1927) PR 19
New-York Historical Society
- Series IV: Dancers
  Series IV contains prints that are among Genthe's most poetic and purely artistic. They capture a watershed moment in dance performance, when the aesthetic began to change from classical to modern; these developments are exemplified most dramatically by the shots of Isadora Duncan and her dancers, the Marion Morgan Group, and the Ritual Dancers of St. Mark. While to modern eyes some of the props and articulations - the flowing Grecian robes, the urns and "palace" settings, maidens frolicking through the woods - may border on parody, they represent something revolutionary: a breaking free of Victorian constraints, a sudden liberty of the female form. Two rather more sophisticated photographs, of Anita Zahn and Margaret Severn dancing at ocean's edge, utilize the same "exotic" costuming (flowing, sheer robes) and naturalistic setting. The remainder of the prints are rooted more in the theater: Tilly Losch and Harald Kreutzberg in "Orientalist" pose and costuming (another popular aesthetic in the early 20th century); Uday Shan-Kar and Simkie, who brought traditional Indian dance to Manhattan; and the well-known "La Argentina" (Antonia Merce), in classic flamenco pose. The prints in the series range from about 9 by 7 inches to 13 by 10 inches; all are black and white. Photographs are arranged alphabetically by last name, title, or description.
  - Duncan, Isadora, [1906-1927] (Offsite-box 6, Box 12, Folder 91)
    10-1/4 x 13-3/8 inches; signed "Arnold Genthe, N.Y."
  - [Group of five dancers], [1906-1927] (Offsite-box 6, Box 12, Folder 92)
    11-2/16 x 16-3/16 inches
  - [Group of six dancers], [1906-1927] (Offsite-box 6, Box 12, Folder 93)
    10-7/16 x 12-11/16 inches
  - [Group of three dancers], [1906-1927] (Offsite-box 6, Box 12, Folder 94)
    10-1/2 x 13-11/16 inches; stamped "Vanity Fair" on verso
  - "La Argentina" (Merce, Antonia), [1906-1927] (Offsite-box 6, Box 12, Folder 95)
    13-1/4 x 9-1/4 inches; signed "Arnold Genthe, N.Y."
  - Losch, Tilly, and Kreutzberg, Harald, [1906-1927] (Offsite-box 6, Box 12, Folder 96)
    13-5/16 x 9 inches; includes Genthe's studio label
    For Tilly Losch, see also Box 5, Folder 40
  - Losch, Tilly, and Kreutzberg, Harald, [1906-1927] (Offsite-box 6, Box 12, Folder 97)
    13 x 8-1/2 inches; includes Genthe's studio label
  - "Marion Morgan Group", [1906-1927] (Offsite-box 7, Box 13, Folder 98)
    9 x 11-13/16 inches; signed "Arnold Genthe, N.Y."; includes his studio label
  - "Ritual Dancers of St. Marks", [1906-1927] (Offsite-box 7, Box 13, Folder 99)
    12-15/16 x 9-7/8 inches; "Guthrie Dancers," an alternate name, inscribed on verso
  - Severn, Margaret [dancing at water's edge], [1906-1927] (Offsite-box 7, Box 13, Folder 100)
    12-3/8 x 9-5/8 inches
  - Shan-Kar, Uday, and Simkie, [1906-1927] (Offsite-box 7, Box 13, Folder 101)
    13 x 9-13/16 inches; signed "Arnold Genthe, N.Y."; includes his studio label
  - [Single dancer], [1906-1927] (Offsite-box 7, Box 13, Folder 102)
    13-1/4 x 8-1/4 inches
  - [Two dancers], [1906-1927] (Offsite-box 7, Box 13, Folder 103)
    9-1/16 x 6-7/8 inches
  - Zahn, Anita [dancing at water's edge; color print], [1906-1927] (Offsite-box 7, Box 13, Folder 104)
    7-3/4 x 6-1/4 inches; signed "Arnold Genthe, N.Y."
- Series V: Cats
  Series V contains only four prints, though each appears to be quite lovingly composed, attesting to Genthe's admitted lifelong passion for felines. None of the prints are dated, but given other factors and events in Genthe's life, it is estimated they were shot in the 1920s. The prints are approximately 10 inches by 13 inches, or the reverse, and are arranged alphabetically by title. Genthe's adored cat Buzzer (he had four to whom he gave that name) is featured in at least two of the photographs: One has Buzzer curled up on a chair, resting his head on a Chinese doll that is almost his size; the other shows Buzzer contentedly lounging on a couch. A third shot is of a cat (possibly Buzzer) perched atop wine barrels, sun and shadows playing off barrels and cat. The fourth was taken of a cat in a courtyard in New Orleans, when Genthe visited that city in the early 1920s and took a number of architectural shots.
  - "Buzzer", [1919-1929] (Offsite-box 7, Box 14, Folder 105)
    8-11/16 x 13-7/16 inches; signed "Arnold Genthe, N.Y."; includes his studio label
  - "Cat and Wine Barrels", [1919-1929] (Offsite-box 7, Box 14, Folder 106)
    13-7/16 x 10-3/16 inches; signed "Arnold Genthe, N.Y."; includes his studio label
  - "Friends" [cat and Chinese doll], [1919-1929] (Offsite-box 7, Box 14, Folder 107)
    10 x 13-3/16 inches; signed "Arnold Genthe, N.Y."; includes his studio label
  - "In a New Orleans Courtyard", [1919-1929] (Offsite-box 7, Box 14, Folder 108)
    12-3/8 x 9-11/16 inches; signed "Arnold Genthe, N.Y."; includes his studio label
- Series VI: Negatives
  Series VI contains numerous subjects in more than 3,200 nitrate and acetate negatives, though only a handful match up with the vintage prints in this collection - perhaps not surprising considering these were a separate acquisition from the Library of Congress. The series includes personalities such as Greta Garbo and J. P. Morgan; Genthe on horseback; numerous sitters for studio portraits; San Francisco's Chinatown; New York City buildings in 1931 and Central Park; Long Island houses, gardens, and hunting grounds; White Sulphur Springs, West Virginia; views of New Orleans, Guatemala, Japan, and various locales in Europe; and dance groups, including Isadora Duncan's troupe and the Marion Morgan group. Dated negatives span 1913-1942, but the size of the Chinatown film negatives suggests that they may be the original 1890s exposures taken with a handheld camera.
  An item list is not available for this series, which contains more than 3,200 items, many of which are duplicates or near-duplicates. However, a database is available for browsing. Probably most useful to researchers is the ability to search by name of sitter or by subject. Of the latter, subjects used for the Genthe's photographs are used in the database as well, in addition to several added subjects: Buildings, Interiors, Art Objects, Documents, and Events.